A Guide to the James Mercer Garnett Papers, 1861-1865
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
James Mercer Garnett Papers, 1861-1865
Library of Virginia
20947
26 leaves and 10 pages
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from J. Mercer Garnett of Baltimore, Maryland, 27 June 1935.
Biographical Information
James Mercer Garnett was born 24 April 1840 in Loudoun County, Virginia, to Theodore Stanford Garnett (1812-1885) and Florentina Isidora Moreno Garnett (1822-1907). He received his M.A. from the University of Virginia in 1859. When the Civil War began, he enlisted in the Rockbridge Artillery, but transferred to become an ordnance officer in Rodes', later Grimes' Division in the 2nd Corps of the Army of Northern Virginia. Garnett was a professor at the University of Virginia from 1882 to 1896. He married Kate Huntington Noland (1849-1919), daughter of Burr Powell Noland (1818-1889) and Susan Champline Noland (d. 1872) of Loudoun County, and they had one son. Garnett died 18 February 1916, and was buried in the Sharon Cemetery in Middleburg, Loudoun County.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1861-1865, of James Mercer Garnett (1840-1916) of Virginia, consisting of agreements, certifications, invoices, letters, lists, military orders, military passes, paroles, permits, receipts, and requisitions. Papers contain a request by Garnett to be discharged from the Rockbridge Artillery for assignment elsewhere and military orders assigning Garnett to various duties in the Confederate Army. Papers also include invoices, receipts, and requisitions for military stores to various military units in the Shenandoah Valley; and agreements, orders, and paroles relating to the surrender of the Army of Northern Virginia at Appomattox Court House. Also contains military passes, one for Miss K. H. Noland (1849-1919) from the Confederate War Department to travel on the railroads and one for Garnett to travel as a paroled officer; certification that Garnett has been paid in late 1864 and early 1865; letter from R. M. T. Hunter (1809-1887) to General Edward O. C. Ord (1818-1883) vouching for Garnett's character; permit from President Andrew Johnson (1808-1875) to B. P. Noland (1818-1889) allowing him to remain in Loudoun County, Virginia, if he takes the oath of allegience; and a list of number of men and arms, possibly taken at Appomattox.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically
Item List
- Request, 20 November 1861, by James M. Garnett for discharge from the Rockbridge Artillery, part of the Army of the Potomac (C.S.A.). Discharged approved by commanding officer., 1 leaf.
- Special Orders No. 573, 7 December 1861, headquarters of the Army of the Potomac (C.S.A.), assigning Lieutenant James M. Garnett to the Valley District., 2 pages.
- Special Orders No. 232, 11 December 1861, headquarters, Valley District, assigning Lieutenant James M. Garnett to duty with Captain J. H. Waters' Company of Artillery., 2 pages.
- Special Orders No. 270, 23 December 1861, headquarters, Valley District, assinging Lieutenant James Garnett as Chief of Ordnance., 2 pages.
- General Orders No. 39, 22 April 1862, headquarters, Valley District, relieving Lieutenant J. M. Garnett from duty as Chief of Ordnance., 1 leaf.
- Special Orders No. 203, 22 April 1862, headquarters, Valley District, assigning Lieutenant J. M. Garnett to the Army of the Valley., 1 leaf.
- Special Orders No. 12, 25 April 1862, headquarters, 1st Brigade, Valley District, granting Lieutenant J. M. Garnett a leave of absence for business connected with the Ordnance Department., 1 leaf.
- Invoice, 1 May 1863, of stores to be transported to Lieutenant Colonel B. G. Baldwin from the Richmond Arsenal., 2 pages.
- Invoice, 1 May 1863, of stores to be transported to Lieutenant Colonel B. G. Baldwin from the Richmond Arsenal., 1 leaf.
- Invoice, 23 June 1863, of stores to be transported to Lieutenant Colonel R. L. Walker, Staunton, Virginia, from the Richmond Arsenal., 1 leaf.
- Invoice, 23 June 1863, of stores to be transported to Lieutenant Colonel R. L. Walker, Staunton, Virginia, from the Richmond Arsenal., 1 leaf.
- Receipt, June 1863, for stores received at Staunton, Virginia, by Lieutenant Colonel R. L. Walker., 2 leaves.
- Requisition, 8 June 1863, for pistol caps from Captain S. G. Brown., 2 pages.
- Requisition, 8 June 1863, for pistol caps from Captain S. G. Brown., 1 leaf.
- Invoice, 23 June 1863, of stores to be transported to Lieutenant Colonel B. G. Baldwin, Staunton, Virginia., 1 leaf.
- Invoice, 23 June 1863, of stores to be transported to Lieutenant Colonel B. G. Baldwin, Staunton, Virginia., 1 leaf.
- Receipt, June 1863, for stores received at Staunton, Virginia, by Lieutentant Colonel B. G. Baldwin., 2 leaves.
- Pass, 2 September 1864, from the Confederate States of America War Department to Miss K. H. Noland of Loudoun County, Virginia, to visit Charlottesville, Virginia. Contains a description of Miss Noland and her oath of allegiance., 2 pages.
- Certification, 11 February 1865, by Captain A. J. Whitlock that Captain J. M. Garnett has been paid for the period 30 November 1864 to 31 January 1865., 1 leaf.
- Parole, 9 April 1865, for prisoners of war belonging to the Army of Northern Virginia, not signed., 1 leaf.
- Parole, 9 April 1865, for prisoners of war belonging to the Army of Northern Virginia, not signed., 1 leaf.
- General Orders No. 9, 10 April 1865, headquarters, Army of Northern Virginia, concerning the surrender of that Army to the Army of the Potomac., 1 leaf.
- Special Order No. ---, 10 April 1865, issued by General Ulysses S. Grant promising paroled Confederate soldiers safe conduct to their homes., 1 leaf.
- Agreement, 10 April 1865, pertaining to the surrender of the Army of Northern Virginia., 1 leaf.
- General Orders No. 43, 11 April 1865, headquarters, 24th Army Corps, concerning proof of parole and safe conduct for those possessing such proof., 1 leaf.
- Pass, 10 April 1865, for Captain James M. Garnett, a paroled prisoner., 2 pages.
- Letter, 15 April 1865, from R. M. T. Hunter to Major General Edward O. C. Ord, U.S., Richmond, Virginia, pertaining to the character of Captain James M. Garnett., 1 leaf.
- Permit, 21 July 1865, from President Andrew Johnson, Washington, D.C., to B. P. Noland of Loudoun County, Virginia, allowing Noland to remain at his home in Loudoun County if he takes the oath of allegiance., 1 leaf.
- List, n.d., of number of men and arms, possibly taken at Appomattox Court House., 1 leaf.